Finding Aid for Michigan Historical Records Survey records, 1936-1942
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Survey of County Records
  For Historical Materials, broad-ranging essays or compilations of information are filed first, followed by specific topics: location, derivation of name, geography and geology, Indian occupation, French penetration, English succession, American emergence, the Territory of Michigan, creation of the county (including copies of early deeds and mortgages), the county seat of justice, first (and usually subsequent) county officers, politics, the circuit court, the courthouse(s) and other early county buildings, the townships, agriculture, the chief city or cities, prominent citizens, business and industry, education, arts, religion, population (including ethnic breakdowns as well as total numbers), special historic and scenic features, transportation (including routes as well as modes), and journalism. Sometimes, previously written guides or parts thereof were used as the basis for new ones, with revisions for the new guide made on a copy of the old one (e.g., Kalamazoo from Alger, Kent from Alger and Calhoun, and others).
  Discarded from the historical materials were: masses of duplicates, including such things as notes that were written up into essays (if the collection contains the essays), rough drafts of published essays (the most advanced draft of an essay was retained if it had not been published, and if duplicates had conflicting or overlapping information, all were saved), and carbon copies; library notes from published works which the Bentley Library has in its collection or which are readily obtained elsewhere, e.g., county histories, censuses, directories, atlases, laws, to name just a few (although if it was too time-consuming to locate the source or if the notes were extremely clear, these notes were retained); information that was irrelevant; and illegible notes.
  Government information was organized by the H.R.S. in two ways: in "legal research" files and in inventories of records held by the various government departments. Survey staff compiled the former in order to write the history of the government organization for each county and to show the workings of each government department. In the current arrangement of the collection, this type of information is called Historical Material - Government Organization. Luther Evans said to a U.S. Senate subcommittee, "It is necessary, if the reader is to understand the relation of each record to the government of the community and to other records, that he have a brief statement of the history, the organization, duties and function of each office of local government, and that he know what legal requirements exist for the keeping of records." The historical material on the government organization is filed separately from the inventory forms (as, indeed, the H.R.S. workers handled it, until it was brought together to produce a published guide), but both obviously cover the same departments: Board of Supervisors, County Clerk, Register of Deeds, Superintendent of Abstracts/Abstract Department, Circuit Court, Circuit Court Commissioners, Friend of the Court, Jury Commission, Probation Officer, Probate Court, Probate Judge's Office, Juvenile Probation Officer, Sheriff, Concealed Weapon Licensing Board, Coroner, Prosecuting Attorney, Tax Allocation Board/Bureau of Taxation, County Treasurer, Controller, County Auditors, Sinking Fund, School Commissioner, Board of School Examiners, County Health Department/Board of Health, County Nurse, Superintendents of the Poor/Poor Commission, County Welfare Agent, Social Welfare Board/Department of Social Welfare/Bureau of Social Aid, Soldiers' Relief Commission, Board of Election Commissioners, Board of Canvassers, Road Commission, Drain Commissioner, County Plat Board, Surveyor, Board of Park Trustees/Parks Department, Sealer of Weights and Measures, Agricultural Agent, Humane Office, Dog Warden, and Game Warden. (n.b., no county had all of these departments, and sometimes there was historical information on a department but no inventory, or vice versa.)
  Inventories of Government Department Holdings were recorded on Volume and Unbound Record Forms (12-13HR). These provide a wealth of information about the records: the title of the record series, inclusive dates, location and storage conditions, labeling, quantity, contents, arrangement and indexing, physical description of volumes, and more. Field workers would fill out one form for each type of record found and send the forms to the central editorial board in Detroit, where archivists and historians directed the editing. In reviewing these forms, the editors frequently had questions or wanted more information. They wrote their questions and comments on "rejection slips", which they then attached to the forms in question and returned to the workers for correction or completion. For accuracy, everything was rechecked. Usually, new information was added to the original forms, making the rejection slips redundant. These slips have been discarded. But if the information was written on the rejection slip instead of the form, both have been saved. Along with superfluous rejection slips, other unneeded items have been discarded as well: blank forms, superseded forms, and duplicates. Sometimes two or even three workers conducted their own separate inventories of the same records and in these cases the most complete form has been saved for each record. When a typed form accompanied a handwritten one, the most legible one has been retained, usually the typed one. There is undoubtedly some duplication still, for sometimes copies of the same records were found in more than one department and were inventoried in both places (for example, numerous departments would file copies of certain records with the county clerk's office and still retain their originals).
  Both in the original survey and in its current form, arrangement was done at the folder level, with (in most cases) each government department having its own folder. The Survey workers assembled the forms for each department but usually did not put them in any particular order (that would come later, when it was time to publish the inventory). This original order has been retained. If there were very few inventory forms for a given county, they have all been placed in one folder and their departments not itemized in the contents list beyond the "Inventory of Government Department Holdings" listing.
  Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (or H.C.A.) was the heading the H.R.S. gave to their description if the storage and arrangement of records. It deals with the way the workers found the records or, if they were conscientious and industrious, the way they themselves organized them if the county officials gave them permission to improve their arrangement. Here the inventory was done by building and by room within a building, using Form 10HR, which was either the County Building Form or the Office or Vault Form. The County Building Form gives the address and location of the building, describes its physical attributes, and tells some of its history. The Office or Vault Form lists the government department to which the records belong; the location of the room within the building; storage conditions such as overcrowding, lighting, ventilation, and fire safety; and the quantity of bound and unbound records. Sometimes the County Building Form contains very detailed information about the buildings where the records were stored, both physical and historical, accompanied by diagrams of floor plans and building facades. An extreme example of this is Saginaw County, where even the fixtures in the bathrooms were described. Usually there was not much duplication, but if the information on the forms had been written into an essay, either published or unpublished, the forms have been discarded. Oversized floor plans and architectural drawings were not microfilmed and are filed alphabetically by county. Smaller ones have been retained in addition to being filmed and are interfiled with the others. Photographs of courthouses and some other early buildings have also been preserved. Researchers interested in the history or architecture of such buildings should consult these folders, the courthouse section of the Historical Material files, and the H.C.A. files. The transcripts of Board of Supervisors' minutes are another source of information on county buildings.
  There are two files dealing with maps. The first, Maps, consists of maps of the counties drawn by H.R.S. workers on letter-size paper in preparation for publication in the guide for each county. Oftentimes there is a map of Michigan with the given county highlighted to show its location, followed by several maps of that county in varying levels of detail, drawn with some care, frequently in color. The best representative sample of each has been retained, with all duplicates discarded. After filming, these maps have been preserved and grouped together, arranged alphabetically by county. In addition, there are a few maps, too large to microfilm or not really related to the H.R.S., which have been removed to the Bentley Library's map collection.
  The second file, Inventory of Maps in the County describes the maps that H.R.S. workers found in the counties. They used Form 15HR, the Maps and Photographs Form, to describe each map in some detail, noting features such as date, size, title or subject, area covered, scale, type of map, artist or author, publisher, place of publication, physical condition, location, and the name of the government department to which it belonged. H.R.S. workers inventoried an unusually large number of maps in Houghton and Keweenaw Counties.
  - Alcona County
    - Correspondence (Reel 1)
    - Draft of Guide (Reel 1)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings (Reel 1)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 1)
  - Alger County
    - Correspondence (Reel 1)
    - Historical Material (Reel 1)
    - Maps (Reel 1)
  - Allegan County
    - Correspondence (Reel 1)
    - Historical Material (Reel 1)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 2)
    - Maps (Reel 2)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 2)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Board of Supervisors (Reel 2)
      - County Clerk (Reel 2)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 2)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 2)
      - Probate Court (Reel 2)
      - Probate Judge's Office (Reel 2)
      - Sheriff (Reel 2)
      - Concealed Weapon Licensing Board (Reel 2)
      - Coroner (Reel 2)
      - Prosecuting Attorney (Reel 2)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 2)
      - Controller (Reel 2)
      - School Commissioner (Reel 2)
      - Board of School Examiners (Reel 2)
      - County Health Department (Reel 2)
      - Superintendents of the Poor (Reel 2)
      - Social Welfare Board (Reel 2)
      - Board of Election Commissioners (Reel 2)
      - Road Commission (Reel 2)
      - Drain Commissioner (Reel 2)
      - Agricultural Agent (Reel 2)
      - Board of Canvassers (Reel 2)
  - Alpena County
    - Correspondence (Reel 3)
    - Historical Material (Reel 3)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 3)
    - Maps (Reel 3)
  - Antrim County
    - Historical Material (Reel 3)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 3)
    - Maps (Reel 3)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 3)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Board of Supervisors (Reel 3)
      - County Clerk (Reel 3)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 3)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 3)
      - Probate Court (Reel 3)
      - Sheriff (Reel 3)
      - Concealed Weapon Licensing Board (Reel 3)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 3)
      - School Commissioner (Reel 3)
      - Board of School Examiners (Reel 3)
      - Election Commission (Reel 3)
      - Road Commission (Reel 3)
      - Surveyor (Reel 3)
  - Arenac County
    - Correspondence (Reel 3)
    - Historical Material (Reel 3)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 3)
    - Maps (Reel 3)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 3)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - County Clerk (Reel 3)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 3)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 3)
      - Judge of Probate (Reel 3)
      - Coroner (Reel 3)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 4)
      - School Commissioner (Reel 4)
      - Department of Health (Reel 4)
      - Welfare (Reel 4)
      - Road Commission (Reel 4)
      - Drain Commissioner (Reel 4)
      - Agricultural Agent (Reel 4)
  - Baraga County
    - Correspondence (Reel 4)
    - Historical Material (Reel 4)
    - Maps (Reel 4)
  - Barry County
    - Historical Material (Reel 4)
    - Maps (Reel 4)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 4)
  - Bay County
    - Correspondence (Reel 4)
    - Historical Material (Reel 4)
    - Maps (Reel 4)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 4)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings (Reel 4)
  - Benzie County
    - Correspondence (Reel 4)
    - Historical Material (Reel 4)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 4)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 4)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 4)
  - Berrien County
    - Correspondence (Reel 4)
    - Historical Material (Reel 4)
    - Historical Material-Townships (Reel 4)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 4)
    - Maps (Reel 4)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 4)
  - Branch County (Reel 5)
    - Historical Material (Reel 5)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 5)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Drain Commissioner (Reel 5)
      - Surveyor (Reel 5)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 5)
  - Calhoun County
    - Correspondence (Reel 5)
    - Historical Material (Reel 5)
    - Maps (Reel 5)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 5)
    - Inventory of Township Government Holdings
      - Athens (Reel 5)
      - Battle Creek (Reel 5)
      - Clarendon (Reel 5)
      - Eckford (Reel 5)
      - Fredonia (Reel 5)
      - Homer (Reel 5)
      - Marengo (Reel 5)
      - Newton (Reel 5)
  - Cass County
    - Correspondence (Reel 5)
    - Historical Material (Reel 5)
    - Draft of Guide-Government Organization (Reel 5)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 5)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 5)
  - Charlevoix County
    - Historical Material (Reel 5)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 5)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Board of Supervisors (Reel 5)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 5)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 5)
      - Judge of Probate (Reel 5)
      - Probation Officer (Reel 5)
      - Tax Allocation Board (Reel 5)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 5)
      - School Commissioner (Reel 5)
      - Superintendents of the Poor (Reel 5)
      - Board of Election Commissioners (Reel 5)
      - Road Commission (Reel 5)
      - Surveyor (Reel 5)
  - Cheboygan County
    - Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - Historical Material (Reel 6)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 6)
    - Maps (Reel 6)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 6)
  - Chippewa County
    - Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - Historical Material (Reel 6)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 6)
    - Maps (Reel 6)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 6)
  - Clare County
    - Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - Historical Material (Reel 6)
    - Maps (Reel 6)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings (Reel 6)
  - Clinton County
    - Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - Historical Material (Reel 6)
    - Maps (Reel 6)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings (Reel 6)
  - Crawford County
    - Correspondence (Reel 7)
    - Historical Material (Reel 7)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 7)
    - Maps (Reel 7)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 7)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Judge of Probate (Reel 7)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 7)
  - Delta County
    - Correspondence (Reel 7)
    - Historical Material (Reel 7)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 7)
    - Maps (Reel 7)
  - Dickinson County
    - Correspondence (Reel 7)
    - Historical Material (Reel 7)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 7)
    - Maps (Reel 7)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 7)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Board of Supervisors (Reel 8)
      - County Clerk (Reel 8)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 8)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 8)
      - Judge of Probate (Reel 8)
      - Sheriff (Reel 8)
      - Coroner (Reel 8)
      - Tax Allocation Board (Reel 8)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 8)
      - School Commissioner (Reel 8)
      - Superintendents of the Poor (Reel 8)
      - Board of Canvassers (Reel 8)
      - Road Commission (Reel 8)
      - Drain Commissioner (Reel 8)
      - Agricultural Agent (Reel 8)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 8)
  - Eaton County
    - Correspondence (Reel 8)
    - Historical Material (Reel 8)
    - Historical Material (cont.) (Reel 9)
    - Maps (Reel 9)
    - Draft of Guide-Government Organization (Reel 9)
  - Emmet County
    - Correspondence (Reel 9)
    - Historical Material (Reel 9)
    - Maps (Reel 10)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 10)
    - Draft of Guide-Government Organization (Reel 10)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 10)
  - Genesee County
    - Correspondence (Reel 10)
    - Historical Material (Reel 10)
    - Maps (Reel 10)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 10)
  - Gladwin County
    - Correspondence (Reel 10)
    - Historical Material (Reel 10)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 10)
    - Maps (Reel 10)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 10)
  - Gogebic County
    - Correspondence (Reel 11)
    - Historical Material (Reel 11)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 11)
    - Maps (Reel 11)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 11)
  - Grand Traverse County
    - Correspondence (Reel 11)
    - Historical Material (Reel 11)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 11)
    - Maps (Reel 11)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 11)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - List of Offices and Field Forms for Each (Reel 11)
      - Board of Supervisors (Reel 11)
      - County Clerk (Reel 11)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 11)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 11)
      - Probate Court (Reel 11)
      - Sheriff (Reel 11)
      - Concealed Weapon Licensing Board (Reel 11)
      - Coroner (Reel 11)
      - Prosecuting Attorney (Reel 11)
      - Tax Allocation Board (Reel 11)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 12)
      - School Commissioner (Reel 12)
      - Poor Commissioner (Reel 12)
      - Board of Election Commissioners (Reel 12)
      - Road Commission (Reel 12)
      - Plat Board (Reel 12)
      - Surveyor (Reel 12)
  - Gratiot County
    - Correspondence (Reel 12)
    - Historical Material-Circuit Court (Reel 12)
    - Maps (Reel 12)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 12)
  - Hillsdale County
    - Correspondence (Reel 12)
    - Historical Material (Reel 12)
    - Maps (Reel 12)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 12)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings (Draft of Guide) (Reel 12)
  - Houghton County
    - Historical Material (Reel 12)
    - Maps (Reel 12)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Board of Supervisors (Reel 12)
      - County Clerk (Reel 12)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 12)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 12)
      - Probation Officer (Reel 12)
      - Sheriff (Reel 12)
      - Concealed Weapon Licensing Board (Reel 12)
      - Coroner (Reel 12)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 12)
      - Board of School Examiners (Reel 12)
      - Health Department (Reel 12)
      - Superintendents of the Poor (Reel 12)
      - Soldiers' Relief Commission (Reel 12)
      - Board of Election Commissioners (Reel 12)
    - Inventory of Maps
      - Houghton County (Reel 12)
      - Houghton (Reel 12)
      - Ripley (Reel 12)
      - Calumet (Reel 12)
      - South Range (Reel 12)
      - Hancock (Reel 12)
  - Huron County
    - Correspondence (Reel 13)
    - Historical Material (Reel 13)
    - Maps (Reel 13)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 13)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Board of Supervisors (Reel 13)
      - County Clerk (Reel 13)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 13)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 13)
      - Circuit Court Commissioners (Reel 13)
      - Probate Court (Reel 13)
      - Concealed Weapon Licensing Board (Reel 13)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 13)
      - School Commissioner (Reel 13)
      - Health Department (Reel 13)
      - Soldiers' Relief Commission (Reel 13)
      - Board of Election Commissioners (Reel 13)
      - Drain Commissioner (Reel 13)
  - Ingham County
    - Correspondence (Reel 13)
    - Historical Material (Reel 13)
    - Draft of Guide-Government Organization (Reel 13)
    - Maps (Reel 13)
  - Ionia County
    - Correspondence and N.Y.A. Workers (Reel 13)
    - Historical Material (Reel 13)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 13)
    - Maps (Reel 14)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 14)
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Board of Supervisors (Reel 14)
      - County Clerk (Reel 14)
      - Register of Deeds (Reel 14)
      - Circuit Court (Reel 14)
      - Friend of the Court (Reel 14)
      - Probate Court (Reel 14)
      - Probation Officer (Reel 14)
      - Sheriff (Reel 14)
      - Concealed Weapon Licensing Board (Reel 14)
      - Coroner (Reel 14)
      - Prosecuting Attorney (Reel 14)
      - County Treasurer (Reel 14)
      - School Commissioner (Reel 14)
      - Board of School Examiners (Reel 14)
      - Superintendents of the Poor (Reel 14)
      - County Welfare Agent (Reel 14)
      - Soldiers' Relief Commission (Reel 14)
      - Board of Election Commissioners (Reel 14)
      - Board of Canvassers (Reel 14)
      - Road Commission (Reel 14)
      - Drain Commissioner (Reel 14)
      - Surveyor (Reel 14)
      - Agricultural Agent (Reel 14)
    - Inventory of Township Government Department Holdings
      - Boston (Reel 14)
      - Easton (Reel 14)
      - Keene (Reel 14)
      - Lyons (Reel 14)
      - North Plains (Reel 14)
      - Orleans (Reel 14)
      - Otisco (Reel 14)
      - Ronald (Reel 14)
    - Inventory of Municipal Government Department Holdings
      - Belding (Reel 14)
      - Hubbardston (Reel 14)
      - Ionia (Reel 14)
      - Lyons (Reel 14)
      - Muir (Reel 14)
      - Pewamo (Reel 14)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 14)
    - Inventory of Artifacts in County (Reel 14)
  - Iosco County
    - Historical Material (Reel 15)
    - Maps (Reel 15)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 15)
  - Iron County
    - Correspondence (Reel 15)
    - Historical Material (Reel 15)
    - Maps (Reel 15)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 15)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 15)
  - Isabella County
    - Historical Material (Reel 15)
    - Maps (Reel 15)
    - Inventory of Maps in County (Reel 15)
    - Inventory of Newspapers in County (Reel 15)
  - Jackson County
    - Correspondence (Reel 15)
    - Historical Material (Reel 15)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 15)
    - Maps (Reel 15)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 15)
  - Kalamazoo County